<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Technology on Jonas Hestdahl</title>
    <link>https://jonash.xyz/tags/technology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Technology on Jonas Hestdahl</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 23:38:13 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jonash.xyz/tags/technology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Unshackle Your Digital Life</title>
      <link>https://jonash.xyz/posts/how-to-live-an-unshackled-digital-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 23:38:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jonash.xyz/posts/how-to-live-an-unshackled-digital-life/</guid>
      <description> Get a Google Pixel phone, so you can install GrapheneOS . I recommend Google Pixel 6a. Very cheap and very good. Get rid of all the apps you don&amp;rsquo;t need Sync your data with SyncThing Create your own NextCloud server Use VimWiki / Obsidian + vim/ neovim to take notes in markdown , and take full ownership over your own data Use Linux on your personal computer(s) Use pass to store your accounts/passwords Don&amp;rsquo;t let proprietary software take your money and own YOUR data Never look back </description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<ol>
<li>Get a Google Pixel phone, so you can install <a

	
	
		href = "https://grapheneos.org/"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		GrapheneOS
	</span>

</a>
. I recommend Google Pixel 6a. Very cheap and very good.
<ul>
<li>Get rid of all the apps you don&rsquo;t need</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Sync your data with <a

	
	
		href = "https://syncthing.net/"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		SyncThing
	</span>

</a>
</li>
<li>Create your own <a

	
	
		href = "https://landchad.net/nextcloud/"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		NextCloud
	</span>

</a>
 server</li>
<li>Use <a

	
	
		href = "https://github.com/vimwiki/vimwiki"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		VimWiki
	</span>

</a>
/<a

	
	
		href = "https://obsidian.md/"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		Obsidian
	</span>

</a>
 + vim/<a

	
	
		href = "https://github.com/neovim/neovim"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		neovim
	</span>

</a>
 to take notes in <a

	
	
		href = "https://www.markdownguide.org/getting-started/"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		markdown
	</span>

</a>
, and take full ownership over your own data</li>
<li>Use <a

	
	
		href = "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		Linux
	</span>

</a>
 on your personal computer(s)</li>
<li>Use <a

	
	
		href = "https://www.passwordstore.org/"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		pass
	</span>

</a>
 to store your accounts/passwords</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t let <a

	
	
		href = "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proprietary_software"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		proprietary software
	</span>

</a>
 take your money and own YOUR data</li>
<li>Never look back</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern Linux Tools</title>
      <link>https://jonash.xyz/posts/modern-linux-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 14:03:56 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jonash.xyz/posts/modern-linux-tools/</guid>
      <description>These modern Linux tools might enhance your workflow fd is a simple and fast file search tool, enhancing the Unix find command. exa is a modern replacement for ls, enhancing file listing with better defaults. dog is a modern, feature-rich DNS client for the command-line. ncdu is a console disk usage analyzer for quick space management. bat is a cat clone with syntax highlighting and Git integration for the command-line. sd is a simple and intuitive find-and-replace CLI tool, aiming to improve upon sed.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="these-modern-linux-tools-might-enhance-your-workflow">These modern Linux tools might enhance your workflow</h2>
<ul>
<li><a

	
	
		href = "https://github.com/sharkdp/fd"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		fd
	</span>

</a>
 is a simple and fast file search tool, enhancing the Unix <code>find</code> command.</li>
<li><a

	
	
		href = "https://github.com/ogham/exa"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		exa
	</span>

</a>
 is a modern replacement for <code>ls</code>, enhancing file listing with better defaults.</li>
<li><a

	
	
		href = "https://github.com/ogham/dog"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		dog
	</span>

</a>
 is a modern, feature-rich DNS client for the command-line.</li>
<li><a

	
	
		href = "https://github.com/rofl0r/ncdu"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		ncdu
	</span>

</a>
 is a console disk usage analyzer for quick space management.</li>
<li><a

	
	
		href = "https://github.com/sharkdp/bat"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		bat
	</span>

</a>
 is a <code>cat</code> clone with syntax highlighting and Git integration for the command-line.</li>
<li><a

	
	
		href = "https://github.com/chmln/sd"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		sd
	</span>

</a>
 is a simple and intuitive find-and-replace CLI tool, aiming to improve upon <code>sed</code>.</li>
<li><a

	
	
		href = "https://github.com/bootandy/dust"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		dust
	</span>

</a>
 visualizes disk usage with an emphasis on clarity, acting as a more intuitive <code>du</code>.</li>
<li><a

	
	
		href = "https://github.com/ducaale/xh"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		xh
	</span>

</a>
 is a friendly and fast HTTP client for the terminal, inspired by <code>curl</code> and <code>HTTPie</code>.</li>
<li><a

	
	
		href = "https://github.com/muesli/duf"

		

	

	

		target = "_blank"
		rel = "nofollow noopener noreferrer"

		>
	
	<span>
		duf
	</span>

</a>
is a modern disk usage utility for the command-line with an intuitive interface.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What Is DevOps</title>
      <link>https://jonash.xyz/posts/what-is-devops/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 13:09:52 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jonash.xyz/posts/what-is-devops/</guid>
      <description>Development (Dev) and Operations (Ops), is a software development and delivery approach.
It emphasizes:
communication collaboration integration automation The goal of DevOps is to improve and speed up the delivery of software applications and services. By fostering a culture where building, testing, and releasing software can happen rapidly, frequently, and more reliably, DevOps has become a key practice in the software industry.
Key Principles of DevOps Continuous Integration (CI): Developers merge their changes back to the main branch as often as possible.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Development (Dev) and Operations (Ops), is a software development and delivery approach.</p>
<p>It emphasizes:</p>
<ul>
<li>communication</li>
<li>collaboration</li>
<li>integration</li>
<li>automation</li>
</ul>
<p>The goal of DevOps is to improve and speed up the delivery of software applications and services. By fostering a culture where building, testing, and releasing software can happen rapidly, frequently, and more reliably, DevOps has become a key practice in the software industry.</p>
<h2 id="key-principles-of-devops">Key Principles of DevOps</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Continuous Integration (CI):</strong> Developers merge their changes back to the main branch as often as possible. Automated tests run with these integrations to catch bugs quickly.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Continuous Delivery (CD):</strong> This practice involves automatically deploying all code changes to a testing or staging environment after the build stage. It ensures that the software can be reliably released at any time.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Automated Testing:</strong> Automation in testing reduces manual workload and speeds up the process of software development and deployment.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Infrastructure as Code (IaC):</strong> Managing and provisioning infrastructure through code instead of through manual processes, improving operational efficiency and cloud management.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Monitoring and Logging:</strong> Keeping track of the performance of applications and infrastructure to quickly respond to issues.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Collaboration and Communication:</strong> Encouraging open communication and collaboration within and between teams to enhance the development process.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="benefits-of-devops">Benefits of DevOps</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Faster Time to Market:</strong> Shortened development cycles lead to faster innovation and a quicker time to market.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Improved Collaboration:</strong> Breaking down silos between teams enhances collaboration and efficiency.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Increased Efficiency:</strong> Automation and streamlined workflows increase the efficiency of the development and deployment processes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Enhanced Quality:</strong> Continuous integration and delivery ensure that quality is maintained through frequent code updates and testing.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Higher Customer Satisfaction:</strong> Rapid deliveries of updates and new features lead to higher customer satisfaction.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>DevOps is not just a set of practices, but a culture that needs to be adopted for its full potential to be realized. By embracing DevOps, organizations can enhance their ability to deliver applications and services at high velocity, thereby outpacing their competitors in today&rsquo;s fast-paced digital world.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
