<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Linux on Jonas Hestdahl</title>
    <link>https://jonash.xyz/tags/linux/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Linux on Jonas Hestdahl</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 23:38:13 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jonash.xyz/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Unshackle Your Digital Life</title>
      <link>https://jonash.xyz/posts/how-to-live-an-unshackled-digital-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 23:38:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jonash.xyz/posts/how-to-live-an-unshackled-digital-life/</guid>
      <description>Unshackle Your Digital Life Get a Google Pixel phone, so you can install GrapheneOS. I recommend Google Pixel 6a. Very cheap and very good. Get rid of all the apps you don&amp;rsquo;t need Sync your data with SyncThing Create your own NextCloud server Use VimWiki/Obsidian + vim/neovim to take notes in markdown, and take full ownership over your own data Use Linux on your personal computer(s) Use pass to store your accounts/passwords Don&amp;rsquo;t let proprietary software take your money and own YOUR data Never look back </description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="unshackle-your-digital-life">Unshackle Your Digital Life</h2>
<ol>
<li>Get a Google Pixel phone, so you can install <a href="https://grapheneos.org/">GrapheneOS</a>. I recommend Google Pixel 6a. Very cheap and very good.
<ul>
<li>Get rid of all the apps you don&rsquo;t need</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Sync your data with <a href="https://syncthing.net/">SyncThing</a></li>
<li>Create your own <a href="https://landchad.net/nextcloud/">NextCloud</a> server</li>
<li>Use <a href="https://github.com/vimwiki/vimwiki">VimWiki</a>/<a href="https://obsidian.md/">Obsidian</a> + vim/<a href="https://github.com/neovim/neovim">neovim</a> to take notes in <a href="https://www.markdownguide.org/getting-started/">markdown</a>, and take full ownership over your own data</li>
<li>Use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux">Linux</a> on your personal computer(s)</li>
<li>Use <a href="https://www.passwordstore.org/">pass</a> to store your accounts/passwords</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t let <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proprietary_software">proprietary software</a> take your money and own YOUR data</li>
<li>Never look back</li>
</ol>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GRUB Bootloader</title>
      <link>https://jonash.xyz/posts/grub-bootloader/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2024 19:17:15 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jonash.xyz/posts/grub-bootloader/</guid>
      <description>First of all, what is GRUB? GRUB is a boot loader, which lets you boot up your system. The abbreviation stands for GNU GRand Unified Bootloader, and is a boot loader package from the GNU Project. GRUB is the primary bootloader for many Linux distributions, allowing users to choose from multiple operating systems or different versions of the same operating system at boot time. It&amp;rsquo;s designed to be highly configurable and supports a wide range of operating systems, not just Linux.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="first-of-all-what-is-grub">First of all, what is GRUB?</h2>
<p>GRUB is a boot loader, which lets you boot up your system. The abbreviation stands for GNU GRand Unified Bootloader, and is a boot loader package from the GNU Project. GRUB is the primary bootloader for many Linux distributions, allowing users to choose from multiple operating systems or different versions of the same operating system at boot time. It&rsquo;s designed to be highly configurable and supports a wide range of operating systems, not just Linux.</p>
<h2 id="why-make-this-guide">Why make this guide?</h2>
<p>The reason I made this simple guide is so you know what to do when you get to <a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Installation_guide">Arch Linux installation guide, chapter 3.8</a>.</p>
<h2 id="grub-features-include">GRUB features include:</h2>
<ul>
<li>The ability to boot multiple operating systems, including Linux, Windows, and macOS.</li>
<li>Support for reading data from various file systems, allowing it to load boot files from these file systems directly.</li>
<li>A flexible and powerful command-line interface that can be used to troubleshoot boot issues.</li>
<li>The capability to load operating systems from a network, which is particularly useful in managed IT environments.</li>
<li>A customizable menu interface that can display graphics and themes, allowing for a visually appealing boot menu.</li>
</ul>
<p>GRUB has evolved over time, with GRUB 2 being the successor to the original GRUB (referred to as GRUB Legacy). GRUB 2 offers improved modularity, portability, and features compared to its predecessor.</p>
<h2 id="installing-grub-efi-in-arch-linux">Installing GRUB EFI in Arch Linux</h2>
<p>First off, we install some packages:</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>sudo pacman -S vim networkmanager grub efibootmgr dosfstools os-prober mtools
</code></pre><p>(Networkmanager is optional, but highly recommended)</p>
<h2 id="enablenetworkmanager">EnableNetworkManager</h2>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>systemctl enable NetworkManager
</code></pre><h2 id="mount-efi-partition">Mount EFI-partition</h2>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>mount /dev/drive /boot/EFI
</code></pre><h2 id="install-grub">Install GRUB</h2>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>grub-install --target=x86_64-efi --bootloader-id=grub_uefi --efi-directory=/boot/EFI --no-nvram --removable --recheck
</code></pre><h2 id="make-grub-config-file">Make grub config file</h2>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>grub-mkconfig -o /boot/grub/grub.cfg
</code></pre><h2 id="reboot">Reboot</h2>
<ul>
<li>Exit the chroot environment by typing <code>exit</code> or pressing <code>Ctrl+d</code>.</li>
<li>Optionally manually unmount all the partitions with <code>umount -R /mnt</code>: this allows noticing any &ldquo;busy&rdquo; partitions, and finding the cause</li>
<li>Finally, restart the machine by typing <code>reboot</code>: any partitions still mounted will be automatically unmounted by <em>systemd</em>.</li>
<li>Remember to remove the installation medium and then login into the new system with the root account</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern Linux Tools</title>
      <link>https://jonash.xyz/posts/modern-linux-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 14:03:56 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jonash.xyz/posts/modern-linux-tools/</guid>
      <description>These modern Linux tools might enhance your workflow fd is a simple and fast file search tool, enhancing the Unix find command. exa is a modern replacement for ls, enhancing file listing with better defaults. dog is a modern, feature-rich DNS client for the command-line. ncdu is a console disk usage analyzer for quick space management. bat is a cat clone with syntax highlighting and Git integration for the command-line. sd is a simple and intuitive find-and-replace CLI tool, aiming to improve upon sed.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="these-modern-linux-tools-might-enhance-your-workflow">These modern Linux tools might enhance your workflow</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/sharkdp/fd"><code>fd</code></a> is a simple and fast file search tool, enhancing the Unix <code>find</code> command.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ogham/exa"><code>exa</code></a> is a modern replacement for <code>ls</code>, enhancing file listing with better defaults.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ogham/dog"><code>dog</code></a> is a modern, feature-rich DNS client for the command-line.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rofl0r/ncdu"><code>ncdu</code></a> is a console disk usage analyzer for quick space management.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/sharkdp/bat"><code>bat</code></a> is a <code>cat</code> clone with syntax highlighting and Git integration for the command-line.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/chmln/sd"><code>sd</code></a> is a simple and intuitive find-and-replace CLI tool, aiming to improve upon <code>sed</code>.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/bootandy/dust"><code>dust</code></a> visualizes disk usage with an emphasis on clarity, acting as a more intuitive <code>du</code>.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ducaale/xh"><code>xh</code></a> is a friendly and fast HTTP client for the terminal, inspired by <code>curl</code> and <code>HTTPie</code>.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/muesli/duf"><code>duf</code></a>is a modern disk usage utility for the command-line with an intuitive interface.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
