<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>CLI on Jonas Hestdahl</title>
    <link>https://jonash.xyz/tags/cli/</link>
    <description>Recent content in CLI on Jonas Hestdahl</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 13:06:35 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jonash.xyz/tags/cli/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Convert SVG to PDF Using Inkscape</title>
      <link>https://jonash.xyz/posts/convert-svg-to-pdf-using-inkscape/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2024 13:06:35 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jonash.xyz/posts/convert-svg-to-pdf-using-inkscape/</guid>
      <description>Convert SVG to PDF Today I learned that if you have Inkscape installed on your machine, you can convert .SVG files into .PDF, using this simple command:
inkscape input.svg --export-filename=output.pdf
Replace input.svg with the name of your SVG file and output.pdf with the desired output PDF file name. Example use case Say you have developed a drawing or mindmap in Excalidraw. You can export this to SVG and then run the command to convert it to PDF.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="convert-svg-to-pdf">Convert SVG to PDF</h2>
<p>Today I learned that if you have Inkscape installed on your machine, you can convert .SVG files into .PDF, using this simple command:</p>
<p><code>inkscape input.svg --export-filename=output.pdf</code></p>
<ul>
<li>Replace <code>input.svg</code> with the name of your SVG file and <code>output.pdf</code> with the desired output PDF file name.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="example-use-case">Example use case</h2>
<p>Say you have developed a drawing or mindmap in Excalidraw. You can export this to SVG and then run the command to convert it to PDF. Very cool!</p>
<h2 id="links-">Links :</h2>
<p>202403245112</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modern Linux Tools</title>
      <link>https://jonash.xyz/posts/modern-linux-tools/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 14:03:56 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jonash.xyz/posts/modern-linux-tools/</guid>
      <description>These modern Linux tools might enhance your workflow fd is a simple and fast file search tool, enhancing the Unix find command. exa is a modern replacement for ls, enhancing file listing with better defaults. dog is a modern, feature-rich DNS client for the command-line. ncdu is a console disk usage analyzer for quick space management. bat is a cat clone with syntax highlighting and Git integration for the command-line. sd is a simple and intuitive find-and-replace CLI tool, aiming to improve upon sed.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 id="these-modern-linux-tools-might-enhance-your-workflow">These modern Linux tools might enhance your workflow</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/sharkdp/fd"><code>fd</code></a> is a simple and fast file search tool, enhancing the Unix <code>find</code> command.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ogham/exa"><code>exa</code></a> is a modern replacement for <code>ls</code>, enhancing file listing with better defaults.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ogham/dog"><code>dog</code></a> is a modern, feature-rich DNS client for the command-line.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rofl0r/ncdu"><code>ncdu</code></a> is a console disk usage analyzer for quick space management.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/sharkdp/bat"><code>bat</code></a> is a <code>cat</code> clone with syntax highlighting and Git integration for the command-line.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/chmln/sd"><code>sd</code></a> is a simple and intuitive find-and-replace CLI tool, aiming to improve upon <code>sed</code>.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/bootandy/dust"><code>dust</code></a> visualizes disk usage with an emphasis on clarity, acting as a more intuitive <code>du</code>.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ducaale/xh"><code>xh</code></a> is a friendly and fast HTTP client for the terminal, inspired by <code>curl</code> and <code>HTTPie</code>.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/muesli/duf"><code>duf</code></a>is a modern disk usage utility for the command-line with an intuitive interface.</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
